Periods.
الدورة الشهرية.
Blood.
الدم.
Menstruation.
الحيض.
Gross.
مقزز.
Secret.
أسرار.
Hidden.
مخفية.
Why?
لماذا؟
A natural biological process
هي عملية حيوية طبيعية
that every girl and woman goes through every month
تمر بها كل فتاة و امرأة كل شهر
for about half of her life.
لفترة تقارب نصف عمرها.
A phenomenon that is so significant
إنها ظاهرة مهمة جداً
that the survival and propagation of our species depends on it.
بحيث أن نجاة و تقدم نوعنا كبشر يعتمد عليها،
Yet we consider it a taboo.
و مع ذلك نعتبرها من المحرمات.
We feel awkward and shameful talking about it.
ونشعر بالإرتباك و الخجل في الحديث عنها.
When I got my first periods,
عندما بدأت لدي الدورة الشهرية لأول مرة،
I was told to keep it a secret from others --
أخبروني بأن أحفظ الموضوع سرا عن الآخرين --
even from my father and brother.
حتى عن أبي و أخي.
Later when this chapter appeared in our textbooks,
و بعد ذلك عندما ظهر هذا الفصل في كتابنا المنهجي،
our biology teacher skipped the subject.
قامت معلمة الأحياء بتجاوز هذا الوضوع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You know what I learned from it?
هل تعرفون ماذا تعلمت منه ؟
I learned that it is really shameful to talk about it.
تعلمت إن من المعيب فعلا الحديث عنه.
I learned to be ashamed of my body.
تعلمت كيف أكون خجلة من جسمي.
I learned to stay unaware of periods
تعلمت أن أكون غير مهتمة بدورتي
in order to stay decent.
كي أبقى عفيفة.
Research in various parts of India
أظهرت البحوث في مختلف مناطق الهند
shows that three out of every 10 girls are not aware of menstruation
بأن ثلاثة من كل عشر فتيات غير واعيات بطبيعة الحيض
at the time of their first periods.
عند بدايات دوراتهن الشهرية الأولى.
And in some parts of Rajasthan
و في بعض أجزاء راجاستان
this number is as high as nine out of 10 girls being unaware of it.
فإن الرقم يرتفع ليصل إلى 9 من كل عشر فتيات لا يعين ذلك.
You'd be surprised to know
و ستدهشون إذا علمتم
that most of the girls that I have spoken to,
بأن أكثر الفتيات اللواتي تكلمت معهن،
who did not know about periods at the time of their first menstruation
اللواتي لم يعرفن عن الدورة الشهرية عند حصول الحيض الأول لديهن
thought that they have got blood cancer
فكرن في أن لديهن سرطان الدم
and they're going to die soon.
و أنهن سيمتن قريبا.
Menstrual hygiene is a very important risk factor
إن النظافة عند الحيض هي عامل يحمل مخاطرمهمة
for reproductive tract infections.
لالتهابات الجهاز التناسلي.
But in India, only 12 percent of girls and women
و لكن في الهند، فقط 12% من الفتيات و النساء
have access to hygienic ways of managing their periods.
يمكنهن الوصول إلى الطرق النظيفة للعناية بدوراتهن الشهرية.
If you do the math,
و لو قمنا بحساباتنا،
88 percent of girls and women use unhygienic ways to manage their periods.
فإن 88% من الفتيات والنساء يستخدمن طرقاً غير نظيفة للعناية بدوراتهن.
I was one of them.
و كنت واحدة منهن.
I grew up in a small town called Garhwa, in Jharkhand,
نشأت في مدينة صغيرة تسمى غارهوا في جهارخاند،
where even buying a sanitary napkin is considered shameful.
حيث يعتبر حتى شراء الحفاظات النسائية شيئا معيباً.
So when I started getting my periods,
لذلك عندما بدأت عندي الدورة الشهرية،
I began with using rags.
بدأت باستعمال قطع من الخرق.
After every use I would wash and reuse them.
و كنت بعد كل استخدام أغسلها لأعيداستخدامها.
But to store them,
و لكن كي أخزنها،
I would hide and keep it in a dark, damp place
كنت أخفيها و أحفظها في مكان رطب و مظلم
so that nobody finds out that I'm menstruating.
كي لا يجدها أحد و يعرف بأنني أحيض.
Due to repeated washing the rags would become coarse,
و بسبب الغسيل المتكرر تصبح الخرق خشنة،
and I would often get rashes and infections using them.
و طالما أصبت بالطفح الجلدي أو الالتهابات نتيجة استعمالها.
I wore these already for five years until I moved out of that town.
و قد استخدمت هذه لخمس سنوات و لحين مغادرتي تلك المدينة.
Another issue that periods brought in my life
و هناك موضوع آخر جلبته الدورة الشهرية في حياتي
those of the social restrictions
و هي القيود الاجتماعية
that are imposed upon our girls and women when they're on their periods.
المفروضة على بناتنا و نسائنا عندما يكن خلال دورتهن الشهرية.
I think you all must be aware of it,
و أعنقد أنكم جميعا منتبهون لها،
but I'll still list it for the few who don't.
و مع ذلك فسأضعها في القائمة من أجل القلائل الذين لا يعرفون.
I was not allowed to touch or eat pickles.
لم يكن مسموحاً لي أكل أو لمس المخللات.
I was not allowed to sit on the sofa or some other family member's bed.
لم يكن مسموحاً لي بالجلوس على الكنبة أو على سرير فرد آخر من العائلة.
I had to wash my bed sheet after every period,
كان علي غسل شراشف السرير بعد كل دورة شهرية،
even if it was not stained.
حتى لو لم تكن ملطخة.
I was considered impure
كنت أعتبر غير نقية
and forbidden from worshipping or touching any object of religious importance.
و ممنوعة من الصلاة أو لمس أي شيء له أهمية دينية.
You'll find signposts outside temples
كنت ترى منشورات في خارج المعابد
denying the entry of menstruating girls and women.
تمنع دخول أي فتاة أو امرأة حائض.
Ironically,
و الغريب في الأمر،
most of the time it is the older woman
أنه في أكثر الحالات كانت النساء المسنات
who imposes such restrictions on younger girls in a family.
هن اللواتي بفرضن هذه القيود على الفتيات الأصغر في العائلة.
After all, they have grown up accepting such restrictions as norms.
و على أية حال، فقد تربين على القبول بهذه التحديدات والقواعد.
And in the absence of any intervention,
و عند غياب أي تدخل،
it is the myth and misconception
فالأساطير والاعتقاد الخاطئ
that propagate from generation to generation.
هي التي تتشر من جيل إلى جيل.
During my years of work in this field,
خلال عملي في هذا الحقل،
I have even come across stories
صادفت حتى بعض القصص
where girls have to eat and wash their dishes separately.
حيث تأكل الفتيات و يغسلن صحونهن بشكل منفصل.
They're not allowed to take baths during periods,
و لا يسمح لهن بالاستحمام طوال الدورة الشهرية،
and in some households they are even secluded from other family members.
و في بعض العوائل يتم حتى عزلهن عن أفراد العائلة الآخرين.
About 85 percent of girls and women in India
حوالي 85% من الفتيات و النساء في الهند
would follow one or more restrictive customs on their periods every month.
يخضعن لواحدة أو أخرى من تقاليد التقييد خلال دوراتهن كل شهر.
Can you imagine what this does
هل تستطيع تصور ماذا يفعل هذا
to the self-esteem and self-confidence of a young girl?
باحترام الذات و الثقة بالنفس لفتاة شابة؟
The psychological trauma that this inflicts,
إن المرض النفسي الذي يسببه هذا،
affecting her personality,
يؤثر على شخصيتها،
her academic performance
و أدائها الأكاديمي
and every single aspect of growing up during her early formative years?
و كل جانب من نموها خلال سنوات تشكيلها المبكرة ؟
I religiously followed all these restrictive customs for 13 years,
و قد تابعت دينياً جميع هذه العادات المقيدة لفترة 13 سنة،
until a discussion with my partner, Tuhin,
حتى غيرت مناقشة مع شريكي، توهين،
changed my perception about menstruation forever.
تصوري عن الحيض بشكل نهائي،
In 2009, Tuhin and I were pursuing our postgraduation in design.
كنا أنا و توهين عام 2009 نتابع دراستنا العليا في التصميم.
We fell in love with each other
و وقعنا في حب بعضنا
and I was at ease discussing periods with him.
و كنت طبيعية في مناقشة دورتي الشهرية معه.
Tuhin knew little about periods.
وكان توهين بعرف القليل عن الحيض.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He was astonished to know that girls get painful cramps
و قد اندهش من معرفة أن الفتيات يصبن بتقلصات مؤلمة
and we bleed every month.
و أننا ننزف كل شهر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah.
أي نعم.
He was completely shocked to know
و قد أصيب بصدمة عندما عرف
about the restrictions that are imposed upon menstruating girls and women
عن التقييدات المفروضة على الحائضات من الفتيات والنساء
by their own families and their society.
من قبل عوائلهن و مجتمعاتهن.
In order to help me with my cramps,
و لمساعدتي في تقلصاتي،
he would go on the Internet and learn more about menstruation.
أخذ بالدخول إلى الأنترنت ليتعلم أكثر عن الحيض.
When he shared his findings with me,
و عندما شاركني بنتائج بحثه،
I realized how little I knew about menstruation myself.
تحققت من قلة ما أعرفه شخصياً عن الحيض.
And many of my beliefs actually turned out to be myths.
و أن الكثير مما أعتقده تبين أنه في الحقيقة خرافات.
That's when we wondered:
وعند ذلك فكرنا:
if we, being so well educated,
لو أننا، نحن المثقفون بشكل جيد،
were so ill-informed about menstruation,
كنا خاطئين في معلوماتنا عن الحيض،
there would be millions of girls out there who would be ill-informed, too.
فسيكون هناك الملايين من البنات في الخارج قليلات المعرفة أيضا.
To study --
و كي ندرس --
to understand the problem better,
لفهم المشكلة أكثر.
I undertook a year-long research to study the lack of awareness about menstruation
فقد أخذت يحثا لمدة سنة لدراسة نقص الاهتمام والمعرفة حول الحيض
and the root cause behind it.
والسبب الحقيقي وراءه.
While it is generally believed
وحيث إن من المعتقد بشكل و عام
that menstrual unawareness and misconception is a rural phenomenon,
إن عدم الوعي بالحيض والأفكار السيئة عنه هي ظاهرة ريفية،
during my research,
خلال بحثي،
I found that it is as much an urban phenomenon as well.
وجدت إنه ظاهرة حضرية كذلك .
And it exists with the educated urban class, also.
و إنه منتشر في الطبقة الحضرية أيضا.
While talking to many parents and teachers,
و عند حديثي مع عدد من الآباء و المعلمين،
I found that many of them actually wanted to educate girls about periods
وجدت إن الكثير منهم يريدون فعلا تثقيف بناتهم عن الدورة الشهرية
before they have started getting their menstrual cycle.
قبل أن يبدأن دورة الحيض عندهن.
And --
و ..
but they lacked the proper means themselves.
لكنهن أنفسهن يفتقدن الوسائل المناسبة.
And since it is a taboo,
و ما دام هذا من المحرمات،
they feel inhibition and shameful in talking about it.
فهن يشعرن بالامتناع و الخجل بالحديث عنها.
Girls nowadays get their periods in classes six and seven,
تحصل الدورة الشهرية للفتيات اليوم بين الصف السادس و الصف السابع،
but our educational curriculum
و لكن مناهج التعليم لدينا
teaches girls about periods only in standard eight and nine.
تعلم الفتيات حول الدورة الشهرية فقط في الصف الثامن والتاسع.
And since it is a taboo,
و بما أنه من المحرمات،
teachers still skip the subject altogether.
تتجاوز المعلمات هذا الدرس تماما.
So school does not teach girls about periods,
لذا لا تدرس المدارس الفتيات حول الدورة الشهرية،
parents don't talk about it.
و لا يتحدث الآباء عنها.
Where do the girls go?
إذا أين تذهب الفتاة؟
Two decades ago and now --
و منذ عقدبن من الزمن و لغاية الآن --
nothing has changed.
لم يتغير شيء.
I shared these finding with Tuhin and we wondered:
شاركت توهين نتائج دراساتي و فكرنا:
What if we could create something
ماذا لو ابتدعنا شيئا
that would help girls understand about menstruation on their own --
لمساعدة الفتيات على فهم الحيض بأنفسهن --
something that would help parents and teachers
شيئا يساعد الآباء و المعلمين
talk about periods comfortably to young girls?
للحديث عن الدورة الشهرية براحة مع الفتيات الصغيرات؟
During my research,
وخلال بحثي،
I was collecting a lot of stories.
جمعت الكثير من القصص.
These were stories of experiences of girls during their periods.
وكانت هذه قصصا عن تجارب فتيات خلال دوراتهن الشهرية.
These stories would make girls curious and interested
وهذه القصص تجعل الفتيات متشوقات ومهتمات
in talking about menstruation in their close circle.
بالحديث عن حيضهن في حلقاتهن المغلقة.
That's what we wanted.
و هذا ما كنا نريده.
We wanted something that would make the girls curious
لقد أردنا شيئا يجعل الفتيات أكثر فضولاً
and drive them to learn about it.
و يدفعهن للتعلم أكثر عن الموضوع.
We wanted to use these stories to teach girls about periods.
أردنا استخدام هذه القصص لتعليم الفتيات عن الدورة الشهرية.
So we decided to create a comic book,
فقررنا أن نبدع كتاباً مصوراً،
where the cartoon characters would enact these stories
حيث تمثل الشخصيات الكرتونية هذه القصص
and educate girls about menstruation in a fun and engaging way.
و تثقف الفتيات عن الحيض بطريفة ممتعة و مشوقة.
To represent girls in their different phases of puberty,
و لتمثيل الفتيات في مختلف مراحل سن البلوغ،
we have three characters.
أصبحت لدينا ثلاثة شخصيات.
Pinki, who has not gotten her period yet,
بنكي، التي لم تبدأ دورتها الشهرية بعد،
Jiya who gets her period during the narrative of the book
و جيا التي تبدأ دورتها الشهرية خلال القصة في الكتاب
and Mira who has already been getting her period.
و ميرا التي بدأت دورتها الشهرية فعلا.
There is a fourth character, Priya Didi.
و هناك شخصية رابعة هي بريا ديدي.
Through her, girls come to know about the various aspects of growing up
ومن خلالها، تبدأ الفتيات بمعرفة الجوانب المختلفة للبلوغ
and menstrual hygiene management.
و طريقة التعامل مع الحيض بشكل نظيف.
While making the book, we took great care
و خلال إعدادنا للكتاب، حرصنا بشكل كبير
that none of the illustrations were objectionable in any way
على أن لا تكون االرسومات قابلة للاعتراض بأي طريقة
and that it is culturally sensitive.
و أن تكون مراعية ثقافيا.
During our prototype testing, we found that the girls loved the book.
و خلال تجربتنا الأولية للكتاب وجدنا أن الفتيات أحببنه.
They were keen on reading it
وكن مهتمات بقراءته
and knowing more and more about periods on their own.
و التعلم أكثر و أكثر عن الدورة الشهرية بأنفسهن.
Parents and teachers were comfortable in talking about periods
و أصبح الآباء و المعلمون يتكلمون براحة حول الدورة الشهرية
to young girls using the book,
مع فتيات صغيرات مستخدمين الكتاب،
and sometimes even boys were interested in reading it.
و كان الأولاد أحيانا مهتمين بقراءته أيضا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The comic book helped in creating an environment
لقد ساعد الكتاب المصور في خلق بيئة
where menstruation ceased to be a taboo.
حيث توقف الحيض عن كونه من المحرمات.
Many of the volunteers took this prototype themselves to educate girls
و أخذ الكثير من المتطوعين الكتاب الأولي لتثقيف الفتيات بأنفسهم
and take menstrual awareness workshops in five different states in India.
و أقيمت ورش عمل للتوعية بالحيض في خمس ولايات مختلفة في الهند.
And one of the volunteers took this prototype to educate young monks
و قام أحد المتطوعين باستخدام الكتاب الأولي لتثقيف الرهبان الشباب
and took it to this monastery in Ladakh.
و أخذه إلى الدير في لاداخ.
We made the final version of the book, called "Menstrupedia Comic"
و أعددنا النسخة النهائية من الكتاب و اسمه (مجلة الحيض)
and launched in September last year.
و طرحناه في سبتمبر من هذا العام.
And so far,
و لحد الآن،
more than 4,000 girls have been educated by using the book in India and --
تم تثقيف أكثر من 4000 فتاة باستخدام هذا الكتاب في الهند و --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
And 10 different countries.
و في 10 دول أخرى.
We are constantly translating the book into different languages
و نحن مستمررون بترجمة هذا الكتاب إلى لغات مختلفة
and collaborating with local organizations
و نتعاون مع منظمات محلية
to make this book available in different countries.
لجعل هذا الكتاب متوفرا في مختلف الدول.
15 schools in different parts of India
و جعلت 15 مدرسة في مختلف أنحاء الهند
have made this book a part of their school curriculum
هذا الكتاب جزءاً من مناهج المدرسة
to teach girls about menstruation.
لتعليم الفتيات عن الحيض.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I am amazed to see how volunteers,
و يدهشني رؤية المتطوعين
individuals, parents, teachers, school principals,
أفرادا و آباءا و معلمين و مدراء مدارس،
have come together
وهم ينضمون إلينا
and taken this menstrual awareness drive to their own communities,
و يأخذون كتاب التوعية بالحيض إلى مجتمعاتهم،
have made sure that the girls learn about periods at the right age
للتأكد من أن البنات يتعلمن عن الدورة الشهرية في العمر الصحيح
and helped in breaking this taboo.
و ساعدوا على كسر هذه المحظورات.
I dream of a future where menstruation is not a curse,
إنني أحلم بمستقبل حيث لا يكون الحيض لعنة،
not a disease,
ولا مرضاً،
but a welcoming change in a girl's life.
بل تغييرا مرحبا به في حياة الفتاة.
And I would --
و أود --
(Applause)
(تصقيق)
And I would like to end this
وأود إنهاء هذا
with a small request to all the parents here.
بطلب صغير من جميع الآباء هنا.
Dear parents,
أيها الآباء الأعزاء،
if you would be ashamed of periods,
إذا كنتم تخجلون من الدورة الشهرية،
your daughters would be, too.
فستخجل ابنتكم كذلك.
So please be period positive.
رجاء كونوا إيجابيين مع الدورة الشهرية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)